when you compare you know Rust or Go
with Scola what are the pros and cons of
the different language designs what's
something that Rust does better than
Scola something that Scola does better
than Rust
>> so Rust is closer to the metal you have
better performance guarantees I guess uh
the fact that Scala is a garbage
collected language means that you always
have some pauses I mean garbage
collection collectors have become quite
quite capable I mean they're brilliant
and the pauses are really very very
small but it's fact it's it's a fact
that you do need a big chunk of memory
to run fast and I guess Rust could could
run in much much smaller memory so I
believe that's that's better for
embedded systems and things like that I
believe right now rust is actually
overused because a lot of people push
sort of rush rust for things higher
higher up in the stack where you a
garbage collector is fine but uh
essentially you you still want to write
code without and that is for me a bit an
exercise in
uh I don't know just intellectual that I
can do it I I don't think really think
there's a there's a big sense in it that
if you have the memory for a garbage
collector you should absolutely use one
because it makes a lot of things uh
simpler so yes of course if given enough
uh brains I can write code around and I
can do that but why should you I I mean
it it it it can be much simpler.
So that was for R. Uh for go is um sort
of a language a bit that that lags
behind. I mean was intentionally
designed to be to be very very small and
essentially to be the standards of the
languages in the '9s. Uh so now they
have gotten generics which is a big
step. So I believe that sort of is sort
of a step forward for that but it's
still a fairly limited language what you
can do which has an advantage that
essentially it is forces a very uniform
style because there's not much of
different things you can do and that's
probably it a culture foster to do
things in a certain way which makes it
easier to essentially read one's other's
programs and and essentially jump in a
new code base and things like that. So I
think that would be my main advantage of
go that I see there.
>> Is it possible to turn off the garbage
collector in Scola?
>> Not in production. Uh so we have some
research that uh would let you use
essentially your own memory allocators
and things like that. Uh uh the the way
let's say Zigg does it. The problem with
that is always that you uh you you can
leak references into memory that you
reclaim and then all hell breaks use
lose essentially your your pointers
point to memory that's undefined and and
so but in in Scala we we now have a very
good way to actually track these
references so we can actually prevent
that statically by the type system that
this will never happen and you can still
have your own allocator. That said, we
haven't really shipped that in
production yet. So, right now, I would
say you use the garbage collector,
escala. Yeah,
>> I see uh a lot on the internet people
comparing Rust and Zigg or kind of a
fierce debate on which one is better.
When you think about Rust versus Zigg,
what are the merits of the two compared
comparing to each other? So what I can
see is ZIK has a really nifty uh compile
time uh uh uh construct uh essentially
inlining where the compiler does smart
inlining and and and that is quite clean
and quite powerful and Rust has has
macros but I think they're more clunky
than there is than the zik version. Um
in Scala we have something quite close
to zik. We also have essentially very a
thing that's based on on inlinining and
optimizations by the compiler. Uh but we
have a restriction which I believe sik
doesn't have and that is that um there
cannot be additional type errors after
inlining. So the thing is you inline and
then the question is is the inline
program guaranteed correct uh so type
correct or might you have type errors.
The typical example where you might have
type errors is C++ templates. In fact
that's quite quite scary in C++ that you
can expand a template and then you get
very very complex type errors and very
very hard to to to debug things. So ZIK
is I believe is much better because the
the inlining mechanism is much ser.
>> When you say inlining can you explain
the concept? Inlining just means that uh
in in Scala we can write inline in front
of a of a function and that means that
the compiler will uh before it starts
code generating. So during the time when
it looks at the type code which are
trees it will take the function body
when it sees a function call to that
function it will take the call and
replace it by the body and then it will
do some optimizations. it can say okay
so here we have essentially an app an
application to let's say a value which
is a lambda and but I know where the
lambda points to so let me forward the
call right to the function uh so and and
with that you can already do quite a bit
of uh essentially optimizations which
are guaranteed because the the inliner
must inline that's not a thing like an
optimizer has essentially discretion
whether they want to inline things or
not and so you can never rely on that
but an an inliner which is uh
essentially a compile time based on the
typer must inline so you can rely on it
and const explore by in in zik and C++
is essentially very similar
>> okay so it's a way to get rid of the
function call or the overhead of a
function call and tell the compiler you
can do more because it's all I guess in
line
>> yeah you reveal the implementation and
That means you you can you can uh the
compiler can do something with that.
>> When you think about all the dynamically
typed languages, um which one stands out
as one that you think is kind of the
best among them?
>> Python is ubiquitous. Um and it has a
nice syntax. It uh a lot of the Python
programs look like they're very easy to
read. So that's definitely an advantage.
and and the other one would probably be
something like scheme uh which is sort
of very grounded in computer science
theory and lambda calculus and things
like that. So both of them are sort of
interesting in their own way but of
course Python is 100 times more popular.
>> If you compare Scola to Python for
instance I guess what are the trade-offs
that the two languages took? I think the
gap is closing because Python now
actually has an optional type syntax and
and a number of type checkers that check
that syntax in Python is getting some of
the features that Scala had since the
beginning like pattern matching is in
one of the the recent Pythons. So I
think actually the gap is closing not
just between Python and Scala but
between a lot of programming languages
in general. There sort of all drift to a
standard set of features which mostly
come from functional programming
actually pattern matching for instance
strong type systems uh generics
polymorphism all these things came from
closures all these things came from
functional programming and so the gap is
closing in that in that sense. Um,
Python is um I think the main advantage
of Scala over Python is that it is it
has a strong type system that is always
on and that gives you essentially
guarantees uh that essentially certain
bad states can't can't can't happen. So
so really can rely on it whereas I think
I believe the Python type system well
it's just syntax. it has a number of
type checkers, but in general there's
there's le you you have fewer guarantees
and I believe it's also the ecosystem
and culture that doesn't value types as
much in Python. So I think that's
probably the main difference. F
syntactically the two languages I think
with Scala 3 are actually also quite
close. So Scala 3 looks a lot like
Python. Um in that sense uh you could
say well can see it as a
is a language that has uh strong types
and uh runs on on different runtimes
than Python or I should say the other
thing with Python which is really great
is that Python is a fantastic glue
language because I can essentially have
very very efficient linkages to to high
performance C++ libraries uh uh pandas
or numpy or things like